Okay, alright בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is כ"ב, Chaf-Beis,
we're a little bit ahead because I'm going to try to do
it so that we can successfully do it without doing the דף
Daf on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So we pick up today at
the bottom of כ"ב עמוד א' Chaf-Beis Amud Aleph and we are
have dealt with here the issue about about why you cannot חוטב
לכלי chatov la-kli inside of a כלי kli and why there's a
difference between whether it's for for קודש kodesh purposes or טהרה tahara
purposes. The basic answer being that people will actually know what to
do whether they're doing it טהרה tahara or קודש kodesh and not
have these problems, but the real concern is because that's the חברים,
chaveirim, the people that are careful about this. The real concern is
about the עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz who are going to be looking
and patterning themselves after it and it seems that they'll even be
be able to be sensitive to what practices are done for טהרה
tahara purposes and what practices are done for תרומה truma purposes and
what practices are done for קודש kodesh purposes and therefore they'll follow
suit and we have to be more scrupulous by קודש kodesh because
by קודש kodesh we have to we're not going to be able
to turn them back. We have to accept their קרבנות, korbanos, we
have to accept what they bring because obviously there's one בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So that need to accept, I mean, and there's the
irony, we don't take their תרומה, truma, we tell them to give
their תרומה truma to a כהן kohen who's an עם הארץ, am
ha-aretz, but we when it comes to the holiest things and the
things that require the greatest care, קדשים, kodshim, there because there's only
one בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash we have to accept it and that's
already foreshadowing what the end of this פרק perek is going to
be about, that at the רגלים regalim we do away when people
are bringing קרבן korban and they're all coming to that one central
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the aspect of unity whatever is is what
dominates and we do away with these distinctions. So because of that,
because we are going to be more accepting of what they bring
in the area of קדשים, kodshim, we have to be more scrupulous
about our behavior in it during the rest of the year to
set a good standard for them, a model for them, in so
in order to make it more acceptable for us to be able
to accept their קרבן korban when they bring it and that's why
there's this greater degree of care that we exhibit by קודש kodesh
as opposed to תרומה. truma. Okay, so that's what we said so
far and then the גמרא Gemara even said that that's why we
accept testimony from עם הארץ am ha-aretz nowadays because of this aspect
of not you know pushing people away and having them break off
and having them completely rejected. The גמרא Gemara in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash context says building their own במות bamos and offering their
own sacrifices, but again it becomes a general mandate not just around
מקדש mikdash but in the application to בית דין, beis din, a
general mandate of building bridges and inclusion and the costs that we
eat from these types of stratification. So now the גמרא Gemara picks
up with the following:
וניחוש לשאלה. v'neichosh l'sha-ila. It is eight lines from the bottom, word
the beginning of the word is שאלה, sha-ila, let's get a little
further Mike, וניחוש לשאלה. v'neichosh l'sha-ila.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, okay I got it, I got why
you're you know you're saying we can accept, we don't have to
worry what they do for תרומה truma because we're not going to
take their תרומה. truma. Fine, we might not take their תרומה, truma,
but aren't don't we have to be concerned that we we borrow
vessels from them? I mean it was not a complete like they
were in חרם, cherem, right? I mean it's funny, that's what you're
trying to get at, you try to get a handle on this.
On the one hand their clothes are like a מדרס, midras, so
you don't want to be touching their clothes you know at least
certainly not if you're a כהן, kohen, if you're not somebody that's
going to or somebody that needs to be careful about eating your
food בטהרה. be-tahara. On the other hand, you know obviously there's regular
interactions, these are the people, they're the workers, they're they're storekeepers and
the people you interact with on a daily basis and like we
borrow vessels from them you know. So what if we now have
to be afraid that everything they handle is טמא? tamei? So we
shouldn't buy you know how we
going how we
able to
borrow vessels from them? So why isn't that a concern? דתנן, detnan,
we learned in a משנה Mishna and here we're going to see
how that plays, how that's sort of acknowledged and plays a role
in various halakhic פסק. psak. We learned in the following משנה Mishna
in עדיות: Eiduyos: כלי חרס מציל על הכל דברי בית הלל. kli
cheres matzil al hakol divrei Beis Hillel.
If you've got a pottery vessel it protects everything, this is what
בית הלל Beis Hillel says. Now the scenario is the following: oh
good I have a whiteboard behind me, you people encourage me to
move at exactly the right time. So anyway here's your
house okay and here's your yeah this'll be your second story that's
your roof no door
you don't need okay there's your one.
Okay anyway and here is your dead body in the house okay
and that causes טומאה tuma to spread throughout the house and causes
everything everything in the you know under the roof to be טמא.
tamei. Now let's say there is a an opening here that's a
טפח tefach wide then the טומאה tuma will go in here and
it'll spread here and cause everything there to be טמא. tamei. Let's
say in this opening you have a כלי חרס, kli cheres, you
have a pottery vessel so since a pottery filling the hole with
the back of the pot. Pottery vessel facing down, here's the underside
of the pottery vessel. So pottery vessels only become טמא Tamei in
through their opening, through their inside, their cavity. So therefore the טומאה
Tumah can't be מטמא metameh it and therefore it's considered to fill
the hole and the top is safe. Okay, and that's what will
happen. Okay. So here's what happens. So let's take a look. So
כלי חרס מציל על הכל דברי בית הלל, Kli cheres matsil al
hakol divrei Beit Hillel, so everything in the second story is safe,
that's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says. בית שמאי אומרים אינו מציל
אלא אוכלים ומשקין וכלי חרס. Beit Shammai omerim eino matsil ela ochlin
umashkin vekli cheres. It only protects food and drink and liquid like
potable liquids and other pottery vessels that are up here.
But if you have people, if you have other vessels that are
not pottery vessels, okay, whatever types of thing you have, you have
your forks and spoons, that's my fork. Looks like a pitchfork.
Anyway, you got your chairs, anyway, everything else is going to become
טמא. Tamei. Now how does it do that partial saving? That's bizarre.
Either it'll either it doesn't do any saving or it does a
complete saving. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר להם בית הלל
לבית שמאי, Amar lahem Beit Hillel leBeit Shammai, so בית הלל Beit
Hillel said to בית שמאי: Beit Shammai: מפני מה? Mipnei mah? What's
going on? Why? אמרו בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amru Beit Shammai leBeit
Hillel, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai said: מפני שהוא טמא על גבי
עם הארץ, Mipnei shehu tamei al gabei am haaretz, because we have
to assume that this pottery vessel, assuming now we're talking about an
עם הארץ's am haaretz house, which is not clear why we're making
that assumption, but the pottery vessel has to be assumed to be
טמא. Tamei. And since it has to assume to be... now by
the way it would not work if it's non-pottery because if it's
a metal vessel or something like that then any surface will become
טמא, Tamei, so it'll become טמא. Tamei. So basically the rule is
that a טמא Tamei vessel will not protect. A טמא Tamei vessel
will not be considered to stop the hole and the טומאה Tumah
will go through it. So if this were a metal or a
wood vessel then any surface to become טמא, Tamei, the טומאה Tumah
from down here would hit it from the מת met and it
would become טמא Tamei and then the טומאה Tumah would go through.
But a pottery vessel because it's only from the inside, if the
bottom side is facing down, it's טהור. Tahor.
So says בית...
fine. Says בית שמאי, Beit Shammai:
but if this is a house someone עם הארץ, am haaretz, then
even if he's claiming his pottery vessel is טהור, Tahor, we have
to assume it's טמא. Tamei. And therefore if it's טמא, Tamei, the
טומאה Tumah will go through. Of course if the טומאה Tumah goes
through then it should go through completely. What's the distinction? Why are
these guys okay and you know and the food and the drink,
here I'll make my little glass and what I'll make for my
food I don't know, anyway, put it on your table and how
come the food and the drink is going to be טהור Tahor
is going to be טמא? Tamei? What's the difference? If it goes
through it goes through. So let's take a look. אמר להם בית
הלל לבית שמאי, Amar lahem Beit Hillel leBeit Shammai, so בית הלל
Beit Hillel said to בית שמאי: Beit Shammai אמרו בית שמאי מפני
שהוא טמא על גבי עם הארץ, Amru Beit Shammai mipnei shehu tamei
al gabei am haaretz, we have to assume that the pottery vessel
is טמא Tamei and ואין כלי טמא חוצץ ve'ein kli tamei chotsets
and a טמא Tamei כלי kli does not divide, does not protect,
you know, separate the bottom from the top, it'll go through.
Wait, could it be reversed? No, this is
טמא, Tamei, this is טהור. Tahor. אינו מציל אלא.
Eino matsil ela.
Oh, I'm sorry, you're right. I got wrong. Okay, thank you. Thank
you. Okay, good. Okay so since you say that the food and
the drink is okay, אמר להם בית הלל, Amar lahem Beit Hillel,
so בית הלל Beit Hillel said to them: והלא טיהרתם אוכלים ומשקין
שבתוכו? Vehalo tihartem ochlin umashkin shebetokho?
But you said that the food and the drink in the upper
attic is okay. אמרו להם בית שמאי, Amru lahem Beit Shammai, so
בית שמאי Beit Shammai, said to them: כשטיהרנו אוכלים ומשקין שבתוכו לעצמו
טיהרנו. Keshetiharnu ochlin umashkin shebetokho le'atsmo tiharnu. We said it was okay
for the עם הארץ am haaretz himself because basically the assumption here
and now here I'm getting more insight into what types of interactions
you know what type of separations they had between the חבר Chaver
and the עם הארץ. am haaretz. We don't eat the food of
the עם הארץ. am haaretz. As we saw from the very beginning,
the primary way in which these טומאת טהרה tumat taharah played out
was with the question about how you're handling your food and therefore
whose food are you eating, who are you eating with? As we
mentioned the other day, right, the whole sort of reason that when
you know that in the Christian Testaments when we find out that
Jesus ate with you know with the he ate with the prostitutes
and with the tax collectors and with the lepers is because he
was breaking down those barriers that stratified society about separating you know
who can you eat with and who can't eat with and a
lot of that had to do with these issues of the degree
of care of טומאת טהרה tumat taharah and so on. So the
primary issue had to do with what you know how טהור Tahor
you have to be to handle the food and the implications of
eating and therefore who are you eating with and whose food are
you eating. So therefore he says look their food we're not going
to eat. So therefore we can tell them it's טהור Tahor because
he sort of said we have to work within their own system.
As we're going to see in a minute if we tell them
it's טמא Tamei because we are saying we assume that this pottery
vessel was טמא, Tamei, they're going to reject that. They're going to
say how dare you tell me my pottery vessel is טמא, Tamei,
I think my pottery vessel is טהור. Tahor. So therefore we have
to work within their own שיטה shittah and therefore say okay according
to your שיטה shittah that your pottery vessels are טהור, Tahor, fine,
your food is טהור. Tahor. You can within the you know to
the same degree your pottery vessel is טהור Tahor your food is
טהור. Tahor. Go ahead and eat it. And there's no risk for
us to telling them that because anyway we don't eat food with
we don't eat their food. Okay so there's not a risk. But
we can't tell them that their that their that their vessels are
טהור Tahor or the or that the people up there are טהור
Tahor because we actually borrow vessels from them and we actually interact
with people.
our interaction with them we have to say that it's טמא tamei
to protect ourselves. But this, which we're not going to interact with,
their food and drink, because we don't eat and drink with them
and we don't eat and drink their food, so that we can
tell them it's טהור tahor and there's no risk to us.
To be able what? I'm not... I'm טמא. tamei.
All right, so anyway, but you know we have to deal with
to the degree we're able to. So let's take a look. Okay,
so when we tell them that כשטהרנו אוכלין ומשקין שבתוכו לעצמו טהרנו,
keshetiharnu ochlin u'mashkin shebetocho l'atzmo tiharnu,
for himself we have made it טהור, tahor, doesn't impact us. אבל
נטהר כלי שטיהרתו לך ולו, aval nitaher kli shetiharto lach v'lo,
but how can you say that the כלים keilim up there are
טהור, tahor, you're making going to make it טהור tahor not just
for him but also לך, lach, for you, you're going to borrow
those vessels. All right, so therefore we have to say that that's
טמא tamei to protect ourselves. Okay, תניא, tanya, now let's spell this
out and then we're going to get back to how this will
apply by the issue of a vessel inside of a vessel. Okay,
but again you are really seeing the implications of the divisions between
עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz and the חברים. chaverim. They would borrow things
from one another, they'd interact with them, they'd have them as workers
as we saw, they would even have them, you know, transporting their
טהור tahor foods, which is interesting how that would work out, that
was the end of the last פרק, perek, but they wouldn't eat
with them and they wouldn't eat their food and it was so
much of it was around the food and around the eating. Okay,
so therefore we're going to make that distinction. תניא אמר רבי יהושע,
tanya amar Rebbi Yehoshua, so Rebbi Yehoshua said, בשני מדבריכם בית שמאי,
boshni m'divreichem Beis Shammai, I am embarrassed from your words Beis Shammai,
like what type, I can't you know, I can't make any sense
of this. It's embarrassing almost to say this distinction. אפשר, efsher, now
it's embarrassing logically, not socially. אפשר, efsher, we'll see, אשה לשה בעריבה,
isha lasha b'areva,
imagine there was a woman in the second attic, in the second
floor, and she was kneading dough in her dough in her you
know dough trough, whatever it's called, the dough
trough? Isn't a trough for like animals? Okay, anyway something else. Anyway,
in her אשה ועריבה טמאים, isha v'areva tmei'im,
so she and the actual vessel she was using are טמאים tmei'im
מה? mah?
Mixing bowl. All right, טמאים שבעה, tmei'im shivah, they're טמאים tmei'im for
seven days because of
טומאת מת, tumas meis, ובצק v'batzek and the dough that she was
handling and that was in the mixing bowl is טהור, tahor, that's
טהור. tahor. I mean it's absurd, right? Or here's another example about
what you would say. לוגין מלאין משקין, login malei'in mashkin, if you
have like you know like barrels or whatever you know vessels filled
with liquids, לוגין טמאי שבעה, login tmei'ei shivah, the vessels are טמא
tamei for seven days ומשקין טהורין, u'mashkin tehorin, and the liquids in
them are טהור. tahor. So it's not just saying A, B and
C is טהור, tahor, D, E and F is טמא. tamei. The
actual things that are directly in contact and handling the food is
טמא טומאת מת, tamei tumas meis, is seven days טמא, tamei, and
the food itself that's being touched and in the vessels is טהור.
tahor. So that's completely absurd. Okay, so אמר לו, amar lo,
so okay, נטפל לו תלמיד אחד מתלמידי בית שמאי, nitpal lo talmid
echad mi'talmidei Beis Shammai, so one of the students of the house
of Shammai came and like attached himself to Rebbi Yehoshua, you know,
came to respond to him. אמר לו, amar lo, so he said
to him, אמור, emor, so Rebbi Yehoshua said tell me what you
wanted... I'm sorry, I skipped a line. אמר לו אומר לך טעמן
של בית שמאי, amar lo omar lach ta'aman shel Beis Shammai,
permit me to explain to you the reasoning of Beis Shammai. אמור,
emor, he said go say. אמר לו, amar lo, he said to
him, כלי טמא חוצץ או אינו חוצץ, kli tamei chotzetz o eino
chotzetz, an impure vessel, would it divide between, you know, prevent the
טומאה tumah from spreading or not? אמר לו אינו חוצץ, amar lo
eino chotzetz, it would not prevent it, the טומאה tumah would spread
through. כלי של עם הארץ, kli shel am ha'aretz, now the vessel
of an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, because presumably we're talking about a
house of an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, טמא או טהור, tamei o
tahor, do we assume that they're טמא tamei or do we assume
that they're טהור? tahor? אמר לו טמא, amar lo tamei, we assume
they're טמא. tamei. Okay, ואם אתה אומר לו טמא, v'im atah omer
lo tamei, now let's say you tell the עם הארץ am ha'aretz
it's טמא tamei and therefore everything in the second story is טמא.
tamei. So then what will be the implication of this? By the
way, I want to parenthetically point out that even though here we're
assuming כלים keilim in the house of an עם הארץ am ha'aretz
are טמא tamei and so on, Beis Hillel says that it's חוצץ
בפני הכל, chotzetz bifnei hakol, right? We're not, we haven't, we're not
sort of explaining Beis Hillel with this, but it's fascinating if we're
presumably we're talking about the same scenario, a house of an עם
הארץ. am ha'aretz. Beis Shammai is splitting what we're doing, Beis Hillel
is saying everything is טהור, tahor, even though the כלים keilim of
an עם הארץ am ha'aretz are presumed to be טמא. tamei. So
that's in itself quite fascinating because here Rebbi Yehoshua concedes, I'll concede
that I'll consider the vessel to be טמא. tamei. Okay, so if
you're going to consider the vessel to be טמא, tamei, if you'll
concede that point, which Beis Hillel did not, Beis Hillel said we're
going to treat it as טהור tahor and prevent the טומאה tumah
from spreading. So but if we're going to treat this as טמא,
tamei, then you should logically say everything here is טמא. tamei. What
would be the implications of that? So it says ואם אתה אומר
לו טמא, v'im atah omer lo tamei, and if you tell the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz it's טמא, tamei, meaning it's טמא tamei and
everything up here is טמא, tamei, so כלום משגיח עליך, klum mashgi'ach
alecha, he's not going to pay any attention to you. He's going
to say how dare you tell me my vessels are טמא. tamei.
You know, you don't want to eat with me, you don't want
to, you know, take my food, that's your decision, but don't you
tell me that I, you know, that I have to treat my
stuff as טמא, tamei, I know it's טהור, tahor, I know better
than you. ולא עוד *Velo od*, and not only that, אלא שאם
אתה אומר לו טמא tamei. *ella sheim ata omer lo tamei*, if
you start telling him, "No, it's טמא tamei. *tamei*," אמר אומר לך
*amar omer lecha*, he'll tell you שלך טהור tahor, ושלו טמא tamei
*shelcha tahor veshelo tamei*. No, mine is טהור tahor. *tahor*, yours is
טמא tamei *tamei*. How dare you tell me such a thing? Okay,
which is quite fascinating, right? It's the cost of, you know, of
sort of of imposing your standards on others who are not prepared,
you know, who don't buy into your standards and, you know, imposing
them with a type of a strong-arm approach. So he's going to
actually he's going to sort of echo a little bit of the
דבנית על עצמו *dibonit al atzmo* what we heard in the earlier
דף *daf*. They're going to just decide that their system is right
and your system is wrong and there's going to be too big
of a cost to this whole thing. One minute. So therefore, we
cannot logically say that everything here is טמא tamei. *tamei*. That then
he'll completely reject it, he won't listen to us at all. So
what we have to do is we have to be able to
concede what we're able to concede. And we can concede the food
because at least we won't be, you know, sort of endangered by
that, you know, it won't impact us, but we won't concede the
other stuff which we will be endangered by. Now you'll tell me,
I don't understand, didn't you already just finish saying that everything in
an עם הארץ am ha'aretz, *am ha'aretz*'s house is טמא tamei, *tamei*?
So what's the, you know, why what does it mean by saying
that this stuff is טהור tahor. *tahor*? Well, here we're talking about
טומאת מת tumat meit, *tumat met*, which is much more severe. So
we might normally consider the stuff to be טמא tamei *tamei*, but
here there's a much bigger implication, right? Of טומאת מת tumat meit
*tumat met* is a much weightier טומאה tumah, *tumah*. So therefore, we
are going to have to, you know, so we'll concede this, you
know, the food for himself, we won't be endangered by it, but
we're going to have to say that the rest is טמא tamei
טומאת שבעה *tamei tumat shiva*, which is even weightier than normally the
טומאה tumah *tumah* of an עם הארץ am ha'aretz *am ha'aretz*. Let
me just finish reading and then I'll take the questions. Okay. ולא
עוד אלא שאם אתה אומר לו טמא tamei אמר אומר לך שלך
טהור tahor ושלו טמא tamei. *Velo od ella sheim ata omer lo
tamei amar omer lecha shelcha tahor veshelo tamei*. וזו טעמן של בית
שמאי *Vezo ta'aman shel Beit Shammai*. That's why בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*
said this. Yet it's logically absurd, you know, that the food in
the vessels is טהור tahor. *tahor* and the vessels is טמא tamei
*tamei*, but we have to concede something in order for the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz *am ha'aretz* to be able to accept the ruling
that we are giving. So מיד הלך רבי יהושע ונשתטח על קברי
בית שמאי *miyad halach Rabbi Yehoshua venishtateach al kivei Beit Shammai*. So
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* went and he prostrated himself on the graves
of בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*. That's fascinating. What? Like, like the whole
of this cemetery where all of בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* was buried?
I mean, you know, anyway. Was, I guess so. Yeah, anyway. And
he, at each one of the graves. Anyway, this reminds you of
the story before about the עד זומם *Ed Zomem*, right? And the...
anyway, he went and he prostrated himself. אמר נענתי לכם עצמות בית
שמאי *Amar naaneti lachem atzmot Beit Shammai*. I have like, you know,
literally, I've responded to you but really means like I, you know,
humble myself to you, the bones of בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*. ומה
סתומות שלכם כך *Uma stumot shelachem kach*, if your things that are
unexplained of yours are so deep and, you know, based on such
good reason, מפורשות על אחת כמה וכמה *meforashot al achat kama vechama*,
how much more so are your reasons which are, you know, more
understood and more explained, more transparent, how much more, you know, obviously
weight is behind those opinions. Even the things that don't make sense
I see make sense, how much more, you know, sort of credit
and seriousness I have to approach everything that you say. Okay, now
there were some questions.
Yes. Question? So one is, if we're saying it's all טמא tamei.
*tamei*, you know, that means we're basically going to be asking this
עם הארץ am ha'aretz *am ha'aretz*, well, you know, was there a
dead body in your house and you know, how long ago was
it and you know what I mean? Like, if we're making these
distinctions?
Right, I mean, there's obviously some interaction here. He's coming to us
for a פסק psak, *psak*, you know, before other times we say
they're not going to listen to us or they don't ask us
for פסק psak. *psak* or whatever. But it seems at least by
טומאת מת *tumat met*, which is very weighty, you know, some of
the other types of stuff, especially all the various מעלות *maalot* and
all those types of things, again, it does seem that by the
טומאת מת *tumat met* he is consulting with us, but we have
to be careful what we're going to say, you know.
And the other point I was going to make is, is the
נטפל לו *nitpal lo*, which just reminds me, I think it was,
was this the same רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* who was נטפל *nitpal*
by the one who wanted to never eat meat because he was...
Oh, you have the same phrase of נטפל לו רבי יהושע *nitpal
lo Rabbi Yehoshua*?
You're saying they're being except...
Oh, that's a nice point. I'd have to check, you might be
right. That's very nice. יישר כח *Shkoach*, yes.
I just like wanted to double check. So this is like a
very clear example of them saying that we הלכה *halacha* should be
X for like very clear public policy reasons and we're going to
say and act like the הלכה *halacha* is Y.
Yes, but again, the way it's being done is a way that
doesn't, you know... with saying that, it's this is less radical than
what we said before, because here we're saying we're going to say
it's טהור tahor *tahor* when it's really טמא tamei. *tamei* because it
doesn't affect us, it only affects them, and anyway, if we were
more stringent it would count it would, you know, then it would
be completely counterproductive. So here we're doing it only in a way
that keeps us protected from that פסק *psak*, whereas on the עמוד
א' *amud alef*, where you had us accepting the stuff the קרבנות
korbanot *korbanot* they brought, you know, the stuff they brought in their
כלים *kelim* for קודש kodesh *kodesh* and you're accepting their testimony, we
were allowing public policy to even override for our concerns. Now again,
override and find a way to justify it within the הלכתי *halachic*
system, not say that it was clearly wrong and we're doing it,
but yes, but so in a way this is less radical because
this is only impacting them.
Although the whole section of טומאת מת *tumat met* ends with him
on top of the קבר *kever*...
On top of the קבר *kever*. Nice point. And the עצמות *atzmot*,
the bones, right?
Is פסק טומאת מת *psak tumat met* comes up in...
oh you've got the קבר סתום *kever satum*. Interesting. Interesting, and your
שוטן here the פתח. petach. I didn't think about that. Very nice.
Okay, and one last line here which I forgot to read. אמרו,
Amru, they said, כל ימיו הושחרו שיניו מפני תעניותיו. kol yamav hushcharu
shinav mipnei taaniyotav. All of his days, his teeth became black because
of his fasts. If you wanted to make the type of literary
comparison you were making, we're talking about allowing them to eat the
food and not eating their food and whatever. And now, anyway, he's
fasting as a תשובה teshuva for having questioned, and not just questioned
בית שמאי'ס Beit Shammai's פסק, but said he's embarrassed about the פסק.
So that was something he felt so bad about he was always
doing תשובה teshuva for that. Okay, קתני מיהא, katani miha,
so that was a lot fascinating, but the upshot of all of
this is, לכו ולא, lecho velo, that when it comes to vessels,
the point is that we borrow their vessels. We don't eat their
food, we don't eat with them, we don't have them eat with
us, but we borrow their vessels. So אלמא שאלינן מינייהו, alma she'alinan
mineihu, so we infer from this that there is no problem that
we do borrow their vessels. That we'll take as a given, and
then we have to work the halakhic implications around that, but we
don't say we're not going to borrow vessels from them. So כי
שאלינן מינייהו, ki she'alinan mineihu, so, if we're going to borrow from
them, how can we not be as scrupulous when, meaning how can
we do stuff by טהרה, taharah, but when we're doing it for
תרומה trumah purposes, we're back to dunking of immersion of a vessel
in a vessel? So it says you don't have to be as
scrupulous when you're doing it for תרומה trumah purposes because obviously you'll
take the care you need to take for yourself, but you don't
have to like never do one vessel in another vessel because even
if they are misled by that example, you know, it won't come
back on you because you're not going to take תרומה trumah from
them. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say, fine, we won't
take תרומה trumah from them, but we'll borrow their vessels and then
we'll use their vessels for תרומה, trumah, so it's all the same
difference. You know, so okay, you say we're not going to take
their food, but we'll take the vessel. But if you use the
vessel for the food, what difference does it make taking the food
or taking the vessel? Either way you have to deal with the
implications. So how can you have a different standard for תרומה trumah
and for קדשים kodashim if they're going to be following your standard
and misled by it and therefore you'll come to borrow their vessels?
So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, here's the answer. כי שאלינן מינייהו מטבלינן להו. ki she'alinan mineihu
matbilinan lehu. No, no, no, no. Yes, we'll borrow their vessels, but
of course before using their vessels we'll take them to the מקווה
mikveh first. Okay? We're happy to borrow your vessels because we'll take
them to the מקווה. mikveh. Which, what's the one thing of their
vessels we can't take to the מקווה? mikveh? כלי חרס. kli cheres.
Which is why not only is the food טהור, tahor, but the
כלי חרס kli cheres is טהור. tahor Because כלי חרס kli cheres
is something we'll never borrow because we can't take it to the
מקווה. mikveh. So we can tell them their כלי חרס kli cheres
is טהור. tahor. But their other vessels we might, we generally borrow
and we dunk in the מקווה. mikveh. Okay? So that we can't
tell them is טהור tahor because it's one thing to dunk it
in the מקווה, mikveh, but if it's טומאת מת, dunking it in
the מקווה mikveh won't help. So therefore, is that, is that clear?
So we can tell them the כלי חרס kli cheres is טהור.
tahor We never borrow כלי חרס kli cheres from them. We're safe.
Okay, we can't tell them their metal vessels in this case are
טהור tahor because what we do normally is we borrow vessels and
dunk it in the מקווה. mikveh. But in this case dunking it
in the מקווה mikveh won't help. We need to know it's טמא
טומאת מת tamei tumat meit and therefore we have to say that
it's טמא. tamei. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara just spells that out
one minute. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ei hachi, if
that's true, נהדרו להו בית הלל לבית שמאי כי שאלינן מינייהו מטבלינן
להו. nehaderu lehu Beit Hillel le-Beit Shammai ki she'alinan mineihu matbilinan lehu.
Why didn't בית הלל Beit Hillel say to בית שמאי, I don't
understand why you're saying the vessels are טמא. tamei Go ahead, anytime
we borrow the vessels it doesn't, it's not going to hurt us,
we'll just dunk it in the מקווה. mikveh. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, there's an obvious answer. The גמרא Gemara says, טמא מת
בעי הזאה שלישי ושביעי. tamei meit ba'ei haza'ah shelishi u-shevii. If it
became טמא tamei through a dead body, it's not enough to dunk
it in a מקווה. mikveh. You need sprinkling of the ashes on
day three and day seven. Okay? ומי לוזי
לז' יומי לא מושאלי אינשי, u-mi luzi le-zayin yomei lo mushali inshi,
and people normally don't borrow a vessel for seven days. And anyway,
we wouldn't want to start getting into the practice of every time
we borrow a vessel we have to bring it to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash to sprinkle the ashes or wherever the ashes of
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah are, right? That would be obviously way
too onerous. So we'll have a general practice of borrowing their vessels
and dunking it in the מקווה. mikveh. We don't have a general
practice of borrowing their vessels and sprinkling the ashes of פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah. So what do we now, so let's take a step
back and see what we know from this. We don't eat their
food. Okay, once their food is טמא tamei, anyway, you can't make
it טהור, tahor. and the basic difference here about all these levels
had to do with who are you eating with and whose food
are you eating and so on. So food completely off base. We
also have to be careful about their clothing because of this issue
of מדרס. midras. On the other hand, interestingly, vessels, we interact with
them, we have them work for us, the whole thing about they
even transport our טהור tahor. food, we had that in the end
of the last פרק, perek, which was fascinating, and vessels we borrow
from them. But as a, as a, as a precaution,
when we borrow vessels, we always go ahead first and dunk it
in the מקווה. mikveh. So therefore, תרומה trumah we don't take from
them. Okay, so that's, so therefore we can go ahead and borrow
vessels. We don't have to be concerned it's טמא. tamei, We're going
to dunk it in the מקווה. mikveh. We do have to know,
however, if it became טמא טומאת מת, tamei tumat meit, which is
this case. But in general, we can borrow vessels and dunk it
in the מקווה. mikveh. So therefore, תרומה trumah we won't take from
them, that's food, and we'll tell them give it to their friend
כהן עם הארץ, Kohen am ha-aretz, but קרבנות korbanot that they bring
in their vessels, that we are going to take from them because
there's only one בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, so that's sort of
a range of things, the degrees, areas of interaction and areas
of protection. the טהרה taharah that we do for קרבנות korbanot related
things 'cause then we will be taking קרבנות from them and they'll
be following our model and therefore we have to exhibit a greater
degree of care whereas by תרומה terumah we don't have to exhibit
the same degree of care because they because we will not be
taking תרומה terumah from them and if we do take their vessels
from them we'll anyway be dunking it in the מקוה. mikvah. Yes.
I'm just making sure I'm understanding the social dynamic of someone that
you would borrow a vessel from and then not trust and feel
like you have to bring it to the מקוה. mikvah. Like why
do you have a relationship where you're borrowing things from them?
I don't understand, they're your next-door neighbor and you ran and you
know and you're in the ערב שבת erev Shabbat and you're in
the middle of doing a recipe and the same way you knock
on the door and say can I borrow two eggs? You say
so here you can't borrow two eggs because it's, you can't
borrow two eggs because it's... but it's different and you look at
them as low and like...
well, okay, so there's an interesting question, right, I mean look, I
guess you're asking two questions, meaning A you don't trust them, okay,
but I don't trust, you know, it's not like I don't trust
you in general, I might totally trust you in business, you might
even be my best friend, although again that's an interesting question how
much did this, as I've been trying to say, it seems that
this really created very significant social barriers as well or social groupings,
not just technical points. Okay, but you're not my best friend, but
you are my next-door neighbor, right, and we're friendly and I say
hi or whatever, even though I wouldn't eat with you. So but
I'll borrow your lawnmower and you'll borrow my lawnmower, right? So why
won't I borrow your... if I need your silverware, you know, maybe
I'll borrow it as well. The fact that it might be טמא,
tamei. I have a way of addressing that, I'll dunk it in
the מקוה. mikvah. But you're right, what I'm trying to do is
say it is more complicated, it's not like they're totally ostracized, right?
There is definitely this stratification, but then there's also these interactions and
so it's a complicated picture.
Yes. Just along these lines, I actually see this as much more
nuanced than we're comfortable living with. In other words, is it like
there's a thousand השקפות hashkafot out there and all sorts of... yeah.
Is this sort of like saying listen I would never tell you
the food's not kosher, the food's kosher in the restaurant, I won't
eat there, it's not careful enough of standards that I'm comfortable applying
to myself. But I wouldn't tell you you're eating טרף. treif. Is
it sort of close to that...?
It's similar, you're right. I mean, the thing is what you're getting
here though is also the need to protect people that are exhibiting
a higher standard. So if you want, you know, it's sort of
like, you know, they have in Israel they have kosher and כשר
למהדרין kosher l'mehadrin type of a thing. So people know like which
standard is being communicated and they can follow it. The difference here
is, is that here it really is טמא tamei. and we're just
saying טהור. tahor I mean we're actually saying something that is counterfactual
in order for you know, which won't hurt us, it's not going
to hurt them, it's not going to hurt us. They anyway would
assume it's טהור tahor. and we anyway are not going to use
it. But we're actually saying something that is false, we're saying it's
טהור tahor. when it's טמא tamei in order because we need to
be able to say that in order for them to listen to
us for the rest of it.
Okay, that's a huge clarification. So it's not that their designating this
as טהור tahor. makes it טהור.
tahor It's counterfactual is the way you're reading this? Right? Exactly, that's
the way I've always read... that's the way I've always read it.
I mean that's... that seems to be what the גמרא Gemara is
saying. Yes. I mean, you know, they anyway are going to treat
it right.
Right. And a short question like how does the פרה אדומה parah
adumah work? In other words, do you have to take something to
the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash?
No, they would distribute it out.
Not in your kitchen.
Not in your kitchen. It would be distributed in various locations. So
but still... but it would often mean...
it would often mean a trip. The פרה אדומה parah adumah center
in town.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, but it wouldn't be one in every town, so
it often would mean a trip. Okay, anyway, let's take a look.
Okay, so now we understand that. So the גמרא Gemara says ואטבילה
למהימני? ve-atvilah le-meheimni?
Now going back to the earlier point. Are you telling me that
you cannot trust the עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz to do a good
טבילה, tevilah, which gets back to this whole issue about the degree
of care we have to show about being... doing our immersion is
because they might, you know, do their immersion incorrectly. So is that
really true that we can't trust them to do a good job
of immersing? Let's take a look. והתניא, ve-hatanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, נאמנים עמי הארץ על טהרת טבילת טמא מת,
ne-emanim amei ha-aretz al taharat tevilat tamei meit, that עמי הארץ amei
ha-aretz are trusted to say that they immersed themselves when they became
טמא למת. tamei le-meit. So if they're trusted to say they immersed
themselves, presumably it means that we can also trust that the act
of immersion was done correctly. And here you're telling me that this
מעלה ma'alah about a כלי keli in a כלי keli is because
we can't trust that they'll do the act of immersion correctly. So
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
בגופו הא בכליו. ha be-gufo ha be-keilav. It's a difference between the
person and the vessels. The person will say they'll be careful, the
vessels, one vessel in another vessel, not. Now why is it? Maybe
in general you exhibit greater care when you're talking about your own
טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah than when you're talking about your vessels. And
also maybe the types of concerns of one vessel in another vessel
don't apply by humans, maybe there are less areas that could be
made... that could go wrong in the case of humans, although there
are a lot of חציצות chatzitzot on humans that you don't have
on a vessel. רבא אמר Rava amar said, אידי ואידי בכליו. idi
ve-idi be-keilav. No, both are talking about the vessels. ולא קשיא, ve-lo
kashya, and it's not difficult. It's not difficult. הא Ha דאמר de'amar
מעולם me'olam לא lo הטבלתי hitbalti כלי בתוך כלי kli betoch kli?
והא veha דאמר de'amar הטבלתי hitbalti אבל aval לא lo הטבלתי hitbalti
בכלי bekli שאין she'ein בפיו befiv כשפופרת keshofelet הנוד, hanod, which is
רבא'ס Rava's concern anyway. The difference is we can trust him, and
this also gets interesting in terms of השגחה hashgacha standards. We can
trust him to say, if he says, "I never did it in
the problematic way, I never did one vessel in another vessel," we'll
trust him. And this is also fascinating, we don't assume they're lying,
okay? We might assume that they're not as careful as they need
to be, they think they're more careful than they really are, but
we don't assume that they're willfully lying. So if he says, "You
can use this vessel, I actually immersed it and I never did
it in a," say, "with a חציצה, chatzitzah, you know, did you
ever do it a כלי בתוך כלי? kli betoch kli No." Well
then, you know, so fine, I can borrow it. But if he
says, "Yeah, it was a כלי בתוך כלי kli betoch kli? but
you know what, I made sure that the opening was big enough,
or I made sure that for some other reason it floated so
the water got between them." So now it's not a question of
lying or not lying, it's a question of if you believe you
exhibited proper care, can we trust that you applied the necessary attention
and care that was needed even if you think you did? So
that's the difference, and that's a big issue, right? Because I mean,
you know, it comes up a lot like, like you know, in
השגחה hashgacha standards, you know, question about like, you know, if you
know, somebody says, you know, "Can I trust somebody? Somebody says, look,
I'm only going to buy you, you know, stuff from הכשר hechsher
stuff and I'll do it all on paper plates and I'll do
this and I'll do that," you know, can you trust the person?
So that's a big discussion, you know, about what you need, you
know, what, which type of people you can trust and what circumstances
and how much if you know the person really is going to,
is trying to accommodate you and all those things. But you know,
but there are two issues that I always tell people. One issue
is, is trusting the person's honesty and sincerity and desire to do
everything as it's needed, and the other is does the person have
the necessary knowledge and attention to even with the, you know, and
attention, that even with the best intentions will be able to make
sure that everything is being done properly? You know, somebody told me
a story like, I mean, it's absurd, but somebody told me a
story once, he said something, "Oh, it's okay, you can get me
like, you know, as long as it has an OU on it,
you know, you can get it." And somebody ate something and in
the end he said, "Well, what is this? This is very strange."
He showed him the OU. He said, "Yeah, I'll show you the
package." Picks up the package, there was an O on the package
and a U on the package.
So, you know, so it's not always about honesty, it's about knowledge
and attention to detail and knowing what you're looking for. So, anyway,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So actually the עם
הארץ, Am Ha'aretz it's fascinating, it's not like we think they're lying,
right? We just think that they tend to be uninformed or not
as concerned about the tiny details as we are concerned about it.
And therefore we actually can believe them when they say, "I did
it in this, I did it in a way which no, which
there would not even be any problems possible." But if they say,
"I did it in a particular way and I was attentive to
the fact and made sure that things, that this was taken care
of," that's where we can't believe them. Did you have a question?
That was the same question of whether they're assuming here that the
person does know all the information and it's just a question of
not being careful, or what you brought up whether they also don't
know enough?
Right, so I think it might be both. I think generally the
assumption that they're not sufficiently informed and maybe not sufficiently attentive, like
you know, what, you know, what they have to worry about all
those tiny little details, etc. But if they actually say that they
did it in a way that none of these issues were even
on the table, then you know, we can, you know, then, then
we can believe them.
But how can they even say if they don't know, if they
don't know in the first place?
Right, so we may have to ask them. So we could ask
him, "Oh, was there, did you, was it ever a כלי בתוך
כלי?" kli betoch kli And they'll say, "Oh no, I never did
that. I always do them individually," right? So they might not be
able to offer that information, but they may be able to respond,
you know.
They live in a society filled with חברים, chaverim, in other words
it's, it's possible that they were actually quite aware of a lot
of things?
Yeah, I mean it's sort of like saying that, you know, I
don't understand, you know, secular Jews live in a society where there
are plenty of Orthodox Jews so obviously they will know all the
details of כשרות, kashrut, you know?
I mean, so I don't know that they would, they... Look, look,
how many people here could say they know all the details of
טומאה וטהרה? tumah vetaharah? Right? It's a, it's a pretty impossible field
to master. I don't think it's fair to assume... But they just
discount even...
Yeah, I don't think you can say the... I think that's the
whole problem with the עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz is that they, they
didn't know these details. Okay, yeah?
Is it even more nuanced? Are we accepting his statement where it's
כלי בתוך כלי kli betoch kli
but not the כשפופרת keshofelet נוד? nod?
No, if he says it was כלי בתוך כלי kli betoch kli,
but in a non-problematic way, we don't accept that. We only, because
then we can't believe that you were attentive enough to that.
But if he says...
No, I mean the distinction... No, if he says, "I never did
a כלי בתוך כלי, kli betoch kli, I never did a כלי
בתוך כלי," kli betoch kli we believe him. If he says, "I
did a כלי kli בתוך betoch כלי kli but I made sure
there wasn't a problem," then we don't accept it. Okay,
so, okay.
ותניא, Vetanya, and similarly we taught in a ברייתא, braita, this is
a support, not a question. נאמן Ne'eman עם הארץ לומר lomar פירות
peirot לא lo הוכשרו. huchsharu. An עם הארץ is believed to say
the fruit never came in contact with liquid and therefore are not
susceptible, אבל aval אינו eino נאמן ne'eman לומר lomar פירות peirot הוכשרו
huchsharu אבל aval לא lo נטמאו, nitme'u, that they became susceptible but
I was careful to make sure they didn't, they didn't. Again, if
the problem was never around, he's believed, generally we believe him, but
we don't believe the attentiveness that is necessary if there's a possibility
of a problem. Okay, הגופא, Hagufa, and now the Gemara goes back.
Is it really true that somebody is believed to say that they
were טבלו tavlu themselves
properly? והתניא, Ve'hatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא, Beraita, חבר שבא
להזות, Chaver she-ba lehazzot, if a חבר, Chaver, right, a non-עם הארץ
comes to be sprinkled the ashes of פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, מזים
עליו מיד. mazim alav mi-yad. We sprinkle the ashes on him immediately,
right? He says, you only sprinkle the ashes on day three and
day seven. He says, it's been day three since I came into
contact with a dead body. Sprinkle the ashes. Fine, we believe him
that it's day three. Okay, however, עם הארץ שבא להזות, Am Ha'aretz
she-ba lehazzot, so an עם הארץ comes to the אפר פרה, Efer
Parah, the, you know, the red heifer ashes center, so in
that case we say to him, אין מזים עליו עד שיעשה לפנינו
שלישי ושביעי. ein mazim alav ad she-ya'aseh lefanenu shelishi ve-shevi'i. We have
him wait till it's day three from the day he comes and
then do the ashes, and then wait for four more days and
then do it again. But we don't trust him that he's already
up to day three. So you see you don't trust him. And
that's a simple question: how many days has it been? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye
says, you know what, you're right. מתוך חומר שהחמרת לו בתחילתו, הקלת
לו בסופו. Mitoch chomer she-hichmarta lo bi-tchillato, hikalta lo be-sofo. Because of
the stringency that you are going to do at the beginning, that
you are going to insist that he has to wait three days,
we're able to be lenient at the end of the process when
it comes to saying that he's done the טבילה. tevilah. Why? Meaning
the point is like this: why are we able to be lenient
when he says he's gone to the מקוה? mikveh? Because he knows
that if there's ever a question raised about him going to the
מקוה, mikveh, you know, we're going to sort of like, you know,
he sees like what the consequences are in terms of the difficulties
that it's going to impose if you know if so in terms
of the amount of time we make him wait in general when
it comes to be טהור. tahor. So let's look at רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi explains it, where's the רש"י? Rashi? מתוך חומר שהחמרת לו
בתחילה כשבא לפניך להזותו, Mitoch chomer she-hichmarta lo bi-tchilla k'she-ba l'fanecha l'hazoto,
ולא המנתו, v'lo hemanto, since you didn't trust him when it comes
to how many days he's waited in order to begin this sprinkling,
הקלת לו בסופו להאמינו על הטבילה, hikalta lo be-sofo le'ha'amino al ha-tevilah,
לפי שהוא נזהר בטבילה כדי שלא יצטרך לו עוד. le-fi she-hu nizhar
be-tevilah kedei she-lo itztarech lo od. He knows that you're suspicious of
him. And since he knows you're suspicious of him, he'll be careful.
So we're strict by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, maybe that's less
frequent, the טומאת מת and the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So we're
very strict in that one area, so he knows that we're suspicious
of him, and if he knows we're suspicious of him, then he's
going to be much more careful to be scrupulous in the other
area. So we don't demand him go to the מקוה mikveh again.
So what allows us to say we trust you that you've gone
to the מקוה mikveh is because you know how that in general
we're suspicious, we're suspicious of you, and therefore we can trust that
you're being really careful about it. Okay. So it's not as pretty
as it was a minute ago, right? A minute ago we had
a general trust, except we were afraid that there would be areas
of lack of care. Here what allows for the general trust is
the fact that in one place we're very suspicious and there's a
high cost when the person has not, you know, done it correctly.
So that allows us to trust them in other areas because they
don't want to pay the cost because they know that we're watching
out on them. So what is it like?
Trust and verify. Okay. I think it's possible that the word is
להזות, lehazzot, right? Because it's נפעל, nifal, like to be sprinkled on.
I accept that correction.
Yeah. Okay. Alright.
So that is the end of that fascinating in terms of the
degree of interaction. We borrow vessels but we dunk them. We trust
them to say they've done it, but in areas that don't require
sort of like high degree of attention and care. But in the
end that was pulled back a little that part of what allows
us to trust them is the fact that in other places we
don't trust them and they pay a high cost and that allows
us to trust them in other areas. Alright, when we've lost our
lead. Alright. אחוריים ותוך. achorayim ve-toch. But that was really I think
a very insight... you know, gave us good insight into that whole
dynamic. Okay. Now the next מעלה ma'alah is that vessels are considered
to have distinctions between their back and their inside and their handles
when it comes to rabbinic טומאה, tumah even though biblically if it
was a biblical טומאה tumah. obviously if one part of the vessel
becomes טמא tamei the whole vessel becomes טמא. tamei. And again, that's
by טהרות Taharot and not by קדשים. Kodashim. So מאי אחוריים ותוך?
Mai achorayim ve-toch? What does this mean? כדתנן, Kidetnan, like we taught
in the משנה, Mishnah, כלי שנטמא אחוריו במשקין, אחוריו טמאים, תוכו אוגנו
אזנו וידיו טהורים. Kli she-nitma achorav be-mashkin, achorav tme'im, tocho, ogno, ozno,
ve-yadav tehorim. So if a vessel, here, right, here's your vessel, okay,
so some liquid, some טמא tamei liquid comes in contact with it,
so biblically if this was דאורייתא טמא, d'oraita tamei, obviously it touches
part of the vessel, the whole vessel becomes טמא. tamei But rabbinically
only the back becomes טמא. tamei. The back is distinct. So this
is טמא. This is I guess an X. And the inside is
טהור tahor. and the handle is טהור. tahor Okay. And if it's
got a lip, if it's a vessel like this, right, you know
it's got like a lip, the lip is considered distinct like the
bent over lip area is distinct and the אזניו, oznav, the ears
are distinct. So only the back, not the lip, not the ear,
not the inside. All of that is טהור.
So in the lower vessels, yes, the outside is טמא
even the part, even the internal
part... No, the inner wall, the
lower one. Yeah. So
this is טמא but the walls themselves on the inside are טהור.
The wall on the inside? Yeah.
Yeah. If the liquid touched the outside, the walls on the outside
are טמא, the handle is טהור and
the walls on the inside are טהור. How far does the טומאה
tumah penetrate in?
I don't know. Just on the outer surface. Okay. It's not like
כלי חרס.
kli cheres. All right.
So anyway, this would never make sense by a biblical טומאה. So
the גמרא Gemara says, נטמא תוכו כולו טמא. nitma tocho kulo tamei.
Now, if the inside however becomes טמא, this now works a little
like a כלי חרס, kli cheres, then everything becomes טמא. Now the
logic of this is, I mean it's very strange, the idea that
the explanation is, is that you would never biblically have liquids under
normal circumstances being מטמא כלי. metamei a kli. A כלי kli can
only become a ראשון. rishon. So the only thing that can be
מטמא כלי metamei a kli is an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Liquids
tend to be always derivatives, they touch something that is טמא. Now,
there is one liquid that is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, and
that is the sort of liquids, you know, that comes from a
זב zav or זבה zavah or a נדה. niddah. People that have
various flows, so their liquid, not only the flow itself, but the
spit and the urine etc. is also an אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
So that is a small category of liquids that can be an
אב. av. So what we have done is we have said that
all liquids that are טמא have the power to be מטמא כלי
metamei a kli because of this one category of the liquids of
a זב zav and a זבה. zavah. So that's a big stringency
because the general rule is, you know, these liquids are שני, sheni,
they're not a ראשון, rishon, they're not an אב, av, they never
should have that power, but because of this one case, we give
these liquids a power to be מטמא כלי. metamei a kli. Because
that's so stringent, we want to make it clear that this is
a purely rabbinic דין din and we do it by creating essentially
this absurdity, that the outside is טמא and the inside is טהור.
Okay, so that's why we have this specifically by טומאה of liquids
and but when it comes to קדשים, kodshim, we don't make those
distinctions, we consider the whole vessel to be טמא.
But that's a טומאה דרבנן. tumah de'rabbanan.
That's all דרבנן, de'rabbanan, right. Yeah. ובית הצביטה. U'veit hatzvita. Now also
this, the
essentially this is like the handle, is distinct. מאי בית הצביטה? Mai
beit hatzvita? What's the handle? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel מקום שצובטין, mekom she-tzovtin, the place that you sort
of, you know, hold on for, or צובתו tzovto might be like
present it, you know, with or וכן
הוא אומר ve-chein hu omer ויצבוט לה קלי va-yitzpot lah kali and
he extended to her, you know, some roasted קלי. kali. So the
thing that you use to extend forth the vessel, the handle essentially.
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Rav Asi amar Rabbi Yochanan מקום שנקיאי
הדעת צובעין, mekom she-nekiyei hadaat tzovim, a place where finicky people used
to, or some say, you know, used to literally it means to
color but it might mean to dip, so where רש"י Rashi explains
it is that you've got a vessel and in the vessel there's
like a little insert here where maybe you put, you know, your
oil, and you've got your, I don't know, you've got your food
here, so you take the food and you dip it into that
little pocket of oil, you know, because they would dip their stuff
into oil and you know for so anyway it would be some
type of a separate insert in the vessel or an indentation in
the
vessel. תני רב ביבי קמיה דרב נחמן Tanei Rav Bibi kamei de-Rav
Nachman כל הכלים אין להם אחוריים ותוך. kol ha-kelim ein lahem achorayim
ve-toch. All vessels don't have a distinction between the back and the
inside, we don't make these distinctions, it's all one thing. אחד קדשי
מזבח אחד קדשי מקדש ואחד קדשי הגבול. Echad kodshei mizbeiach echad kodshei
mikdash ve-echad kodshei ha-gvul. Whether it's the קדשים kodashim that you bring
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or קדשים kodashim that is out
in the outer
provinces. So אמר ליה קדשי גבול מאי ניהו? amar lei kodshei gvul
mai niyu? What are
קדשי גבול? kodshei gvul? תרומה! Terumah! So it sounds like you're saying
that this distinctions don't hold for תרומה. terumah. ותנן, Ve-tanan, but our
משנה mishnah says that's exactly where these distinctions do hold. אחוריים ותוך
ובית הצביטה בתרומה, Achorayim ve-toch u'veit hatzvita bi-trumah, for תרומה terumah purposes
we make the כלי kli considered to be these separate parts. So
גמרא Gemara says דילמא, dilma, maybe when you said קדשי גבול kodshei
gvul you didn't mean תרומה, terumah, maybe there's another type of קדשים
kodshim you have outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash which is what?
חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקדש. Chullin she-na'asu al taharat ha-kodesh. חולין Chullin
that you're treating as if it was קדשים, kodshim, that's קדשי גבול.
kodshei gvul. Okay, כמרתא. kamartas. So you know what? אדכרתן מילתא
דאמר רבה בר אבוה. Adkarten milta de-amar Rabba bar Avuha. You reminded
me of something that רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha said, who
said, אחת עשרה מעלות שנו כאן. achas esrei ma'alot shanu kan. There
are eleven levels. שש בראשונה בין לקדש בין לחולין שנעשו על
טהרת הקדש. Shesh bishonah bein la-kodesh bein le-chullin she-na'asu al taharat ha-kodesh.
The first six apply whether to קדשים kodshim or חולין chullin treated
as קדשים, kodshim, and this is amongst the first six. So this
idea of breaking up the vessel into parts or seeing it as
one would apply equally for קדשי, kodshei, so you would see it
as one equally for קדשים kodshim and for חולין chullin that was
treated as if it was קדשים. kodshim.
That's קדשי גבול. kodshei gvul. חמש אחרונות לקדש ולא לחולין שנעשו על
טהרת הקדש. Chamesh acharonot la-kodesh ve-lo le-chullin she-na'asu al taharat ha-kodesh. Okay,
so again we're repeating that idea. So again this idea of dividing
up the vessel is something that applies to קדש kodesh and also
we are reminded applies to also חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקדש. chullin
she-na'asu al taharat ha-kodesh. It is fascinating again and maybe this is
self-evident, you know, but we talked about this whole idea about after
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and after a lot of these all
these distinctions went away and it created again less of a stratified
society and חז"ל Chazal still found a way to bring this sense
of purity and sanctity in one's eating, not through all of these
טהרה tahara things which created this stratification, and not through it being
תרומה truma and קדשים, kodshim, but through, you know, making first of
all washing hands, which is something we got right at the beginning,
which is reminding us of the whole תרומה truma thing, and making
ברכות, brachos, and if you don't make a ברכה bracha they say
כאילו מעל, k'ilu maal, like you misappropriated הקדש, hekdesh, but those are
things which are very like egalitarian, you know, don't don't create divisions
and so on. So the reason I mentioned it again here is
because the fact that it calls חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש chullin
she'nasu al taharas ha'kodesh and maybe this is self-evident, why are you
treating your חולין chullin על טהרת הקודש? al taharas ha'kodesh? Is it
number, is it that you are like a טהרה, tahara, you know,
nut? You just want everything to be totally טהור because of the
one time you'll be dealing with קדשים kodshim you want to get
into this habit? Or this is the way in which you show
your פרומקייט, frumkeit, so you show your פרומקייט frumkeit by being careful
about טהרה, tahara, so you're going to be super careful? Or is
it because you want to bring some sense of קדושה kedusha into
your normal life, you know? And the idea that it calls חולין
שנעשו על טהרת הקודש chullin she'nasu al taharas ha'kodesh as קדשי גבול,
kodshei gvul, קדשים kodshim out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, also
might, you know, be thinking about how do we bring קדושה kedusha
into a non, you know, in the outside of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So, you know, that might be part of what this
חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש chullin she'nasu al taharas ha'kodesh is doing
with us as well. Okay. הנושא את המדרס נושא את התרומה אבל
לא את הקודש. ha'nosei es ha'midras nosei es ha'truma aval lo es
ha'kodesh. If somebody is carrying a מדרס, midras, like a seat of
a זב zav or זבה, zava, or whatever, you know, or let's
say the example we'll have is a sneaker, something they stood on
or sat on, okay, in one hand they can be carrying תרומה,
truma, a barrel of תרומה truma if such, if it's a pottery
barrel, in the other hand, because then the pottery barrel won't become
טמא because it only becomes טמא on the inside, not on the
outside, and therefore the תרומה truma on the inside is protected, but
the קדשים kodshim we won't let them do that. Okay, is that
clear? The sneaker is an אב, av, the person is a ראשון,
rishon, okay,
so if the vessel in theory wouldn't even have to be a
pottery vessel because if he's a ראשון rishon he can't make a
vessel into a שני, sheini, we already learned, but רש"י Rashi anyway
says it's a pottery vessel, so anyway it's protected because contact on
the outside won't do anything, and therefore the stuff on the inside
is also protected which is תרומה, truma, but if it's קדשים kodshim
we won't allow it. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: קודש
מאי טעמא לא? kodesh mai ta'ama lo? What's the problem? Even if
it's קדשים, kodshim, everything is protected. משום מעשה שהיה, mishum ma'aseh she'hayah,
a story. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מעשה באחד שהיה מעביר חבית
של יין קודש ממקום למקום, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel ma'aseh b'echad
she'hayah ma'avir chavis shel yayin kodesh mimakom l'makom, a person was transporting
a barrel of wine from one place to another that was wine
that was sanctified, going to be used in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, ונפסקה רצועה של סנדלו v'nifsaka retzuah shel sandalo and a strap
from his sandals broke, his shoelace broke, ונטלה והניחה על פי חבית
u'netala v'hinicha al pi chavis and he took it
and he put it on the barrel, ונפלה לאוויר החבית v'nafla l'avir
ha'chavis and it fell into the air of the barrel, and here
you see that we're presumably dealing again with a כלי חרס kli
cheres so any, even when something enters the airspace, it's מטמא metamei
everything inside, ונתמאת v'nitmeis and it became טמא. באותה שעה אמרו, b'osa
sha'ah amru, from that time on they said, הנושא את המדרס נושא
את התרומה אבל לא את הקודש. ha'nosei es ha'midras nosei es ha'truma
aval lo es ha'kodesh. Okay, now what's fascinating is, what was he
doing with a sandal of a זב? zav? Presumably he wasn't a
זב zav himself who was transporting it, that would have been like
a real problem, you don't want a זב zav transporting your your
your קודש kodesh, wine. So I mean רש"י Rashi says it: נפסקה
רצועה של סנדלו מדרס הזב היתה ונטלה בידו.
nifsaka retzuah shel sandalo midras ha'zav haysa
u'netala b'yado. For some reason he was carrying in his other hand
a sneaker of a זב. zav. I don't know what the explanation
is. Okay.
The מדרס midras
is the shoelace,
the מדרס midras is the shoe, and the shoe and the shoelace
and the whole thing is the מדרס midras because a זב zav
stood, wore those shoes. But what this person is doing carrying a
זב's zav shoe, I have no idea.
Anyway, yeah, so
these are
most of these are the whole category
of חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש chullin she'nasu al taharas ha'kodesh is
Tannaitic sources, right? So the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was still standing?
Yeah, but they still wanted to create קדשים kodshim outside. First of
all Tannaitic is post-בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash also, but they wanted to
create קדשים kodshim outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, even if there
was a בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Right, but my only point is, right, that there was
already this inclination potentially to bring part of the מקדש Mikdash even
while it was still standing into the sanctification of your own precinct.
Right, that's what I was trying to say, that you see yeah,
okay no, I'm sorry I wasn't clear enough, but that's what I
was saying, that you see even, I said חז"ל Chazal clearly did
it post-חורבן, churban, but you see here by talking about קדשים kodshim
and קדשי גבול kodshei gvul that it was some degree going on
even pre-חורבן. churban. Okay, באותה
שעה אמרו, b'osa sha'ah amru, at that moment they said, הנושא את
המדרס נושא את התרומה אבל לא את הקודש. ha'nosei es ha'midras nosei
es ha'truma aval lo es ha'kodesh. The גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי,
ei hachi, if you have to be concerned about those types of
scenarios, תרומה נמי, truma nami, so let's be concerned about it even
for תרומה. truma. I mean, come on, just because the case was
קודש, kodesh. it's not a unique scenario that will only happen by
קודש. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הא מני רבי חנניה בן
עקביא היא, ha mani Rabi Chananya ben Akavya hi, this is רבי
חנניה בן עקביא, Rabi Chananya ben Akavya, דאמר לא אסרו אלא בירדן
ובספינה ובמעשה שהיה, d'amar lo asru ela b'Yarden u'v'sfina u'v'ma'aseh she'hayah, and
in a in a in an analogous case when they made a
prohibition or they made, you know, rules based on an event that
occurred, he said they only made it on an exactly parallel case,
they didn't get out of hand and say oh we can never
do this again. So they wanted to sort of Remember that these
problems existed, but they only prohibited in an exactly parallel case. And
the case there that he's talking about was the case of the
Jordan River and a boat and the story that occurred. What was
that story, מאי *mai*? Let's just read this. דתניא *detanya*, it's on
a *Baraita*: לא ישא אדם מי חטאת ואפר חטאת *lo yisa adam
mei chatas ve'efer chatas*, a person can't bring the water of the
*Parah Adumah* and the ashes of a *Parah Adumah*, ויעבירם בירדן ובספינה
*veya'avirem beYarden uveSefina*, and he cannot transport them over the Jordan in
a boat. Okay. ולא *velo*, and not only can it not be
the Jordan River in a boat, but any transportation that is not
rooted in the ground. Okay. ולא יעמוד בצד זה ויזרקם לצד אחר
*velo ya'amod betzad zeh veyizrekem letzad acher*, don't toss them across a
river. ולא ישיטם על פני המים *velo yashitem al pnei hamayim*, and
don't float them across across a river. ולא ירכב *velo yirkav* ירכיב
*yarkiv* ירכב *yirkav* על גבי בהמה *al gabei behemah* ולא על גבי
חבירו *velo al gabei chaveiro*,
and don't—yeah, don't ride on the back of on the back of
of an animal and on the back of your friend, so like
as—you know, and actually have them like again not rooted in the
ground, אלא אם כן היו רגליו נוגעות בקרקע *ela im ken hayu
raglav nog'os bakarka*. The only way you can do that is if
your feet are on the ground at the time; got to be
a really short בהמה *behemah*. Okay, so basically as a basis of
this one time where something happened in the Jordan River that it
became טמא *tamei*, they said that the ashes of *Parah Adumah* can
only be transported by somebody whose feet are on the ground. It
cannot be transported on the back of an animal, it can't be
thrown in the air, it can't be passed over in a river,
it has to be rooted in the ground. Okay. אבל מעבירן על
גבי הגשר *aval ma'aviran al gabei hagesher*, but you can walk on
a—you can walk on a bridge. Okay, if you couldn't walk on
a bridge, I don't know how you'd ever get it across bodies
of water. A bridge is considered the ground. ואינו חושש *ve'eino choshesh*,
and you don't have to worry. אחד ירדן ואחד שאר נהרות *echad
Yarden ve'echad shear neharos*, whether the Jordan or whether other rivers. וחנניה
בן עקביא אומר *veChananya ben Akavia omer*—לא אסרו אלא בירדן ובספינה וכמעשה
שהיה *lo asru ela beYarden uveSefina uchema'aseh shehayah*. No, they only limited
it to the exact scenario of the one problematic case that occurred,
which was the Jordan River and a boat. מאי מעשה שהיה *mai
ma'aseh shehayah*? What was the story? דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב *d'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, מעשה באדם אחד שהיה מעביר מי חטאת ואפר
חטאת בירדן ובספינה *ma'aseh be'adam echad shehayah ma'avir mei chatas ve'efer chatas
beYarden uveSefina*, he was transporting the ashes and the water of *Parah
Adumah* across the Jordan in a boat, ונמצא כזית מת תחוב בקרקעיתה
של ספינה *venimtza kezayit mes tachuv bekarkaitah shel sefina*, and they found
a—you know, an olive-size of a dead body, of the flesh of
a corpse on the bottom of the boat, and therefore it made
everything in the boat טמא *tamei* and it ruined everything. Okay. באותה
שעה אמרו *be'otah sha'ah amru*, לא ישא אדם מי חטאת ואפר חטאת
ויעבירם בירדן ובספינה *lo yisa adam mei chatas ve'efer chatas veya'avirem beYarden
uveSefina*. They said don't do this across the Jordan and a boat.
And חנניה בן עקביא *Chananya ben Akavia* said that's the only thing
they said, exactly that, whereas presumably others came back and said no,
they didn't mean just that, they meant anything alike that, and abstracted
it to be this huge prohibition of any type of transporting that
isn't rooted on the ground. So in parallel here, you had a
case that was with a shoelace and a barrel and קודש *Kodesh*.
So one approach is fine, we'll keep that restriction by קודש *Kodesh*,
but we're not going to get out of hand and the other—as
opposed to a potential logic that could be let's just never allow
you to transport something while you're carrying you know a מדרס של
זב *midras shel zav*, whether it's קודש *Kodesh*, whether it's תרומה *terumah*,
whatever it might be.
So these containers were not כלי חרס *klei cheres*?
In the case there? Yeah, it wouldn't matter because it's the—the roof
would carry it you know if it was on a lower level
of the boat, the roof would carry it and it would go—it
wouldn't only hit the bottom of the כלי חרס *klei cheres*. Okay,
if it was a higher roof than the כלי חרס *klei cheres*.
Let's just get to read the it's the—מיבעי להו *itba'i lehu*—that's the
question: סנדל טמא סנדל טהור מהו *sandal tamei sandal tahor mahu*? Let's
say it's not—we know it's a problem if it's a—impure sandal. Maybe
we should never let somebody carry any types of sandals, even טהור
*tahor* sandals when you're carrying קודש *Kodesh*. Don't carry sandals. Okay, as
long as we're abstracting and generalizing. Or חבית פתוחה *chavit pesucha*,
we know the problem was with an open barrel, but חבית סתומה
מהו *chavit stuma mahu*? What would it also apply if you're carrying
a sealed barrel? עבר ונשא מהו *avar venasa mahu*? How about *bedi'avad*?
Maybe you're not allowed to do it *lechatchila*, what would be the
status *bedi'avad*? So רבי אילא *Rabbi Ila*—אמר רבי אילא *amar Rabbi Ila*—עבר
ונשא טמא *avar venasa tamei*. He—so at least the last point we
know that there's two opinions. רבי אילא *Rabbi Ila* says *bedi'avad* it's
טמא *tamei*. רבי זירא אמר עבר ונשא טהור *Rabbi Zeira amar avar
venasa tahor*. No, *bedi'avad* it's okay, it's only a *lechatchila*. Okay, so
here was a particular event and becomes an interesting question of how
much do we abstract and generalize to cases that are not that
are not similar. Okay, we'll end here. All right.